Guide to the Socialist Labor Party Seattle Section Records
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
Socialist Labor Party Seattle Section records
1930-1962
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
3180
3180-001
Socialist Labor Party (Wash.).$bSeattle Section
2.73 cubic feet 7 boxes
Records of a Seattle political labor organization
The Seattle Section of the Socialist Labor Party (SLP) was founded in the early 1890's as a branch of the Socialist Labor Party of America. The SLP was founded as a Marxist political party in 1876, the first nationwide socialist party in the United States. The party promoted the doctrines of Daniel DeLeon, theorist of the SLP, which advocated a classless, stateless, industrial democracy in which private property would be abolished and all natural resources and means of production would be operated by the workers through Socialist Industrial Unions. The SLP planned to achieve its goals through national and local elections and by capturing the trade union movement. However, the party's narrow sectarian ideology, its insistence on doctrinal unity and party discipline, together with its rejection of social reform alienated it from the trade union movement. After modest success in the 1890s, the party declined and never numbered more than a few thousand. It survived however, and continued to run candidates for national and state office.
The Socialist Labor Party was the first socialist organization of any importance in the Pacific Northwest but it never established ties with the labor movement and never developed beyond a small cadre. During the period documented by these papers, 1930-1962, the Section frequently consisted of fewer than six active members and at times, particularly in the early 1950s, nearly ceased to exist. Section Seattle experienced frequent internal dissent, occasionally expelled members and was, in 1944, itself censured, expelled from the Party and reorganized. The business of the Section was carried on by an organizer who was democratically chosen and who reported to the secretary of the State Executive Committee. The State Executive Committee answered to the National Executive Committee which was headed by the National Secretary, an office held by Arnold Peterson throughout this period. The official organ of the Party was the Weekly People, which the Section sold through subscriptions and newstands. Its other activities included the sale of SLP pamphlets, distribution of leaflets, lectures, classes and social activities. The SLP in Washington held an annual convention and also conventions to nominate candidates for state elections.
Arranged in 4 series:
Administrative records
Primary conventions
State Executive Committee
Spokane Section
Correspondence, minutes, financial records, conventions and ephemera of the Seattle branch of a Marxist, socialist political party; 1930-1962 (bulk 1943-1962).
Includes records of the Washington State Executive Committee (SEC)(1944-1962) and the Spokane Section (1943-1944). The records of the SEC Secretary consist primarily of SEC Minutes and the 1949 correspondence of Theodore Bossie, who was then SEC Secretary but also a longtime member and former organizer of Section Seattle. Bossie apparently kept his SEC files at the Seattle Section, and his correspondence coincides with a gap in the Seattle correspondence.
Major correspondents and approximate dates of service:
Section Seattle:
George Bennett - section organizer, 1940-November 1943
Oscar Lindberg - section organizer, November 1943-January 1945
Ray Solie - section organizer, January 1945-July 1945
Erven O. Hebert - section organizer, July 1945-1949
Alexander Merson - section organizer, October 1950-Augist 1951
Ray Berner - section organizer, January-July 1957
Jack Ceder - section organizer, July 1957-July 1959
Donald Orcutt - section organizer, August 1959-1960
Charles W. Turner - financial secretary, 1957-1960
State Secretary:
Frank Daniels, 1943-1944
Al Meenk, 1944
Theodore Bossie, 1944-1949
Ernest O. Sturm, 1951-1957
Henry Killman, 1957-1960
National Socialist Labor Party:
Arnold Peterson - National Secretary
Herb Steiner - Regional representative circa 1944
View inventory/container list
Open to all users.
Gift of Budget Rent-A-Car, May 8, 1981.
The records of Section Seattle of the Socialist Labor Party were discovered in a closet of the International Order of Good Templars Hall by members of the lodge and were offered to the Library. After approval was granted by Budget Rent-A-Car, the purchaser of the property, the material was transferred to the Library in May 1981, shortly before the building's demolition. Why or when the records were abandoned is not known.
Issues of the Weekly People which were received with the papers were relocated to the University of Washington Libraries' Microform and Newspaper Collection. Books from the SLP library were added to the University of Washington Libraries' main collection.
Socialist Labor Party (Wash.).$bSeattle Section$vArchives; Bossie, Theodore$vCorrespondence; Petersen, Arnold, 1885-1976$vCorrespondence; Steiner, Herbert$vCorrespondence; Socialist Labor Party (Wash.).$bSpokane Section; Socialist Labor Party (Wash.).$bState Executive Committee; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); Spokane (Wash.)$xPolitics and government; Washington (State)$xPolitics and government$y1889-1950; Washington (State)$xPolitics and government$y1951-; Political parties$zWashington (State)$zSeattle$vArchives; Socialist parties$zWashington (State)$zSeattle$vArchives; Political conventions$zWashington (State); Political parties$zWashington (State); Socialist parties$zWashington (State); Socialism$vPeriodicals; Correspondence; Ephemera; Financial records; Minutes; Proceedings; Weekly People
Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor History; Labor Unions; Political Campaigns; Seattle; Politics and Politicians
- Administrative records
  - Organizational features, 1943, 1945 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - General correspondence, 1933, 1942-1962 (Box-folder 1/2-2/7)
  - Intra-organizational correspondence
    - National Executive Committee (Arnold Petersen, National Secretary), 1938-1962 (Box-folder 2/8-3/20)
    - Weekly People, 1943-1961 (Box-folder 3/21-25)
  - Minutes
    - Section Seattle (bound volumes), 1930-1952 (Box-folder 3/26-4/7, Box-folder 4/7)
    - Washington State Convention, 1943-1962 (Box-folder 4/8)
    - National Convention, 1948, 1950, 1951, 1960 (Box-folder 4/9)
  - Financial records
    - Audit records (bound volumes), 1940-1964 (Box-folder 4/10-5/5)
    - Annual reports, 1942-1961 (Box-folder 5/6)
    - Membership dues, 1941-1949 (Box-folder 5/7)
    - Membership contributions, 1937-1943 (Box-folder 5/8)
    - Miscellany, undated (Box-folder 5/9)
  - Reports
    - Local organizer report, 1943 (Box-folder 5/10)
    - Section activity report, 1943-1961 (Box-folder 5/11-15)
    - Grievance committee, 1949 (Box-folder 5/16)
    - Miscellany, 1943-1961 (Box-folder 5/17-19)
  - Speeches and writings, undated (Box-folder 5/20)
  - Newsletters, 1943-1962 (Box-folder 5/21-6/2)
  - Elections
    - Vote tally, 1943-1960 (Box-folder 6/3)
    - National Party Constitution, 1942-1960 (Box-folder 6/4)
    - National Executive Committee, 1942-1962 (Box-folder 6/5)
  - Clippings, undated (Box-folder 6/6-7)
  - Ephemera, undated (Box-folder 6/8-11)
- Primary conventions
  - Minutes, 1942-1948 (Box-folder 6/12)
  - Certificates of nomination and related papers, 1944-1948 (Box-folder 6/13-15)
- State Executive Committee
  - General correspondence, 1944-1949 (Box-folder 6/16-19)
  - Intra-organizational correspondence - National Executive Committee, 1949 (Box-folder 6/20-24)
  - Minutes, 1943-1962 (Box-folder 6/25-7/4)
  - Reports
    - Section activity reports, 1949 (Box-folder 7/5)
    - Biennial convention, 1958-1960 (Box-folder 7/6)
- Spokane Section minutes, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 7/7)